<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ScrollView xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:layout_height="match_parent"
    android:layout_margin="10dp"
    android:background="@drawable/shape_background"
    android:gravity="center"
    android:orientation="vertical"
    android:padding="10dp" >

    <TextView
        android:layout_width="fill_parent"
        android:layout_height="fill_parent"
        android:text="
Chapter 1: Introduction

1: Purpose

2: The Time We’re Talking About

3: How to Use This Book

4: “Win At Waiting”

 

Chapter 2: Time is Precious

1: Time as Discrete Moments

2: Continuous Time

3: The Value of Time

4: A Brief History of Clocks

 

Chapter 3: Waiting

1: Waiting Can Be a Waste of Time

2: Why People Don’t Like to Wait

3: Waiting Can Be Good For You

4: How to Enjoy Waiting

 

Chapter 4: Approaches

1: Two Basic Choices

2: Do Something

3: Don’t Do Anything

4: Add Some Variety to Your Routine

5: Old Standbyes

6: New Standbyes

7: Planning and Preparation

8: Avoid Waiting

9: Advanced Techniques: How to Save Time Using Public Transportation

 

Chapter 5: Situations

A: Circumstances

2: Situations

3: Worksheet

4: Answers

 

Chapter 6: For Further Study

1: Bibliography

2: Join the Community

3: Quotes

 

About the Author

 

Acknowledgements

 

 

Chapter 1: Introduction

How can you get more done without piling on stress? How can you create more time for family and friends?

1: Purpose

The pace of life is fast and getting faster. The purpose of this book is to help you get done more of what you want to do without piling on stress. It started out over fifteen years ago as an idea I thought could contribute something to the peace of the world, by reducing the frustration that arises from the combination of two aspects of the human condition: (1) we wait a lot, and (2) most people don’t like to wait. I hope that this book will reduce your stress and friction in relationships.

We’re not going to lower stress by raising the level of anxiety over how productive we are. Many people already feel overloaded and can’t or don’t want do any more. What we need instead is to start to do things differently.

If you can turn your waiting into something that is productive and enjoyable you will probably be less resentful when your colleagues, friends, and family make you wait.

Waiting is easier to do if you have something productive or enjoyable to do to pass the time. Much of what follows is common sense, but you may pick up some new ideas here and there. In any case, the time spent thinking about the subject will make you more conscious of this aspect of time management, and may help create a new habit.

2: The Time We’re Talking About

This book deals with fairly short periods of time, from about ten seconds to one hour. The seconds and minutes that you save will add up though over the course of the months and years.

Let’s start with some sobering statistics about how we spend time doing a few of life’s common activities. If you are not sober, do not wish to become so, or just aren’t in the mood right now to digress, you may skip ahead to the next section, “How to use this book”.

It has been estimated that we wait on the average of 45-60 minutes a day, which adds up to 2-5 years over the course of a lifetime. 6 months of that is at traffic lights, and one entire year is spent in line. Some labor saving machines are time saving as well. Having your own washing machine can save you the 54 hours a year you’d otherwise be spending, along with the quarters, at your neighborhood laundramat.

A lot of time is spent on endeavors that aren’t exactly waiting, but are equally as unproductive, such as the average 199 hours a year spent commuting to and from work—more time than American’s typically get for vacation. It has been predicted that during your lifetime you will spend 8 months opening junk mail, and one year looking for lost possessions. A survey by a British clothing company found that the average woman spends 287 of her days deciding what to wear, often in an anxious state.

There are a variety of reasons people watch TV—to escape, relax, have company when alone, share with others, or catch up on the news. Seen from a distance, watching TV looks like a form of waiting—a passive activity that one sinks into until it is time to do the next thing. But remember Democritus’ adage: “Penny wise, pound foolish”. While he was talking about money, observing those who are careful spending pennies but careless with larger sums, the idea can also be applied to time as well. Why bother rescuing a few minutes here and there if you’re devoting years of your life to watching television? Blow up or recycle your TV if you are serious about saving time!

It has been estimated that the average American watches more than four hours of TV a day, or nine years by the age of 65. The average child spends 900 hours a year in school, but 1500 hours watching TV. One of the negative results for children of watching a lot of TV is that it reduces opportunities to learn to use their imagination as a form of entertainment. By the age of 18 a child will have viewed about 200,000 violent acts, and by the time they reach 65 years old will have sat through 2 million commercials.

Negative non-time related consequences of TV abuse include health results of a sedentary lifestyle combined with the high-calorie diet encouraged by its ads for junk food. Actresses on TV are 23% thinner than 95% of the female viewers, contributing to problems of self-image, which can lead to bulimia or anorexia.

The mental processes required to process the combination of moving images and sounds easily stifle original thoughts. It hardly matters what the program is—the quickly changing camera angles, dialog, sound effects, and music suck you in.

Many viewers show patterns of watching that are reminiscent of warning signs of substance abuse:

Using TV as a sedative

Watching by yourself

Indiscriminate watching

Neglecting your responsibilities

TV causes problems in your relationships

Feeling out of control while watching

Feeling guilty or angry at oneself afterwards for watching too much

Your life revolves around watching

You are unable to stop watching

Feeling miserable when unable to watch

 

What can you do if you’re not ready to get rid of entertainment screens altogether? Try becoming more active, like the gang on Mystery Science Theater. Stay alert by talking back to the TV, question and mock commercials, comment on the story, and discuss why the program uses the images and approach that it does. Hit the mute button on your remote control whenever a commercial comes on, hop up, and do some stretching or knee bends. Sitting is bad for your health!

3: How to Use This Book

There are plenty of lists out there of suggestions for things you can do while you wait.  While there are some ideas for specific activities in Chapter 5, the point of this book is to develop a strategy for coming up with your own ideas, and for deciding which thing to do in any situation.

You can read this book while you are waiting. Though we start out with some theory, this is primarily an activity book, so you’ll get the most out of it if you take notes while you read.

4: “Win At Waiting”

I agree with Thomas Carlyle that “a person usually has two reasons for doing something: a good reason and the real reason.” The good reason for putting “Win” in the title for this book was that one of its meanings is “overcoming difficulties and reaching one’s goals.” It’s OK to think of “winning” in this sense of finishing first in a competition if it gives you an energy boost to get started developing new habit, but hopefully over time the greater enjoyment of your time will be enough to keep you on track without always needing to be number one.

The real reason for using the word “Win” was that the book needed a short and snappy alliterative title, and the “w” in “win” goes well with “waiting”.

 

 

 

Chapter 2: Time is Precious

Like light, time can be seen is discrete quanta or as a wave.

1: Time as Discrete Moments

Time is one of the seven fundamental physical quantities in the International System of Units.

Sir Isaac Newton subscribed to the realist point of view, in which time is viewed along with space and numbers as part of the fundamental structure of the universe. Newton called this “mathematical time”, an abstraction of the advancing seconds, minutes, and hours indicated by clocks. According to the length of time being considered, time is measured by clock or calendar.

Precise measurements of time were initially of interest scientists and technologists due to its importance in navigation and astronomy. Lawyers continue to be prefer this way of looking at time, since it allows them to bill their clients for each minute put in on cases.

2: Continuous Time

The second basic way to look at time is as a gestalt, an entire configuration taken all at once that cannot be evenly divided into smaller units.

Einstein was the first to show that light has both quanta and wave properties. Einstein proved that time is relative, and current theories include the idea that time is just a direction, and created out of space: “The separation between past, present, and future is only an illusion, although a convincing one.”

Time looked at as a wave is less susceptible to division into discrete units, more like a container that events and objects move through. Henry David Thoreau called time “The stream I go a-fishin in.” Continuous time flows like a stream, smoothly connecting one moment to another. The rate of time’s passing varies depending on how fast we are going, and how engaged and deep into the flow we are.

The wave view of time can provide relief from the pressure of schedules, appointments, and deadlines that we face during the day. Marking the passing of time this way, and by the long cycles derived from moon phases and seasons results in a continuous, more leisurely perception of time than the seconds marked by a ticking clock. Sundials track the gradual continuous movement of the sun across the sky, and are only expected to be precise to about an hour. Bali lies near the equator, and the people who there, like those who live in other tropical climates, did  not traditionally need a calendar to stay on track in order to remind them to put aside food, for cold seasons, as those who live closer to the poles have to in order to have food during cold seasons. The native calendar in Bali is different from that of industrialized countries. Its cycles indicate “full” days on which something of importance happens (i.e. an elaborate temple celebration), and “empty” days on which less goes on.

3: The Value of Time

Capitalist societies value achievement, and the pressure to succeed can lead to anxiety. The level of time pressure varies depending on the time of day, the day of the week, season of the year, whether you’re at home, on the street, at work, or on a holiday. It is easy to bring the time reference experienced for many hours on the job back home after work. Once you catch yourself reacting like you do on the job it’s good to stop and slow down and release the tension.

Benjamin Franklin was a practical person, and his quote “Time is money” has become a cultural meme. Our looking at time in financial terms is revealed when we use words like “spending”, “saving”, and “investing” in relation to time. In some ways time is like money. Time is a precious resource, and the amount you have left in your lifetime is a basic asset. Don’t waste too much of it. “Killing time” should be a misdemeanor, or at least a ticket-able offense.

In other ways, however, time and money are quite different. It’s possible to get a pretty exact accounting of one’s financial wealth, but how much time one has to live is a mystery. Money began as a way to facilitate trade, but time cannot be exchanged or saved. You can’t buy time, not because it has no value or wouldn’t have a market. While you can reduce the amount you waste, you can’t save what is left over. Taking short cuts or avoiding wasting time just leaves you time to do other things. Use what you’ve saved wisely or there will be no net benefit. When you get to the end of your life people are more likely to wish that  they had more time than more money.

A habit is a learned behavior that you do without having to devote your full attention to it, saving you the mental processing you would otherwise have to do. Whether they are good habits or bad habits depends on what the outcomes are. Like a hybrid car that automatically shuts off the motor at stoplights to save energy, you can switch into time-conservation mode more quickly if you have a habit for for doing so. I hope that you can use this book to create habits to use time more constructively.

To make good habits requires effort though. These tips may help:

Set your goals. What habit(s) can help you achieve them?

Know what habit you want. Write it down.

Make a list of benefits of the new habit and visualize them.

Commit to doing what you would like to become a habit for 30 days. Scientists say it will take 21 days, or about 30-40 repetitions to grow a habit to perform a simple repetitive task. Be consistent. A new way of thinking could take longer. Don’t skip a day.

Consult a friend. Find a buddy who would like to work on developing the same habit.

Start slowly, simply.

Do it the right way. Make it work best for you and your companions.

Make it fun. Mix things up.

Set a time. Make a schedule. Decide on a daily situation in which you can apply the habit.

Place reminders around so you won’t forget.

Try it out and see afterwards whether you like the results.

Repeat the action frequently enough to reinforce it.

Keep track of the time you save. Reward yourself by spending that time on something you enjoy.

The frustration we feel over wasting time will be explored further in Chapter 3. You can skip ahead to it now, or use a couple of minutes reading about the development of time pieces, which are responsible for promoting the quantum view of time.

4: A Brief History of Clocks

The study of time and timekeeping devices is called horology, and those interested in such are called horologists. Clocks have evolved from sundials, water clocks, and hourglasses to mechanical clocks, pendulums, electronic clocks, and atomic clocks.

The ancient Babylonians are credited with dividing an hour into 60 minutes, and minutes into 60 seconds. The clocks in 13th century towers signaled the hours for religious services. Some of the first table clocks built in the 15th century had one hand and divided hours into four segments. By the 16th century clocks were accurate to within a minute. This allowed Tycho Brahe to make more precise astronomical measurements that Kepler used to deduce laws of planetary motion. In the 17th century Galileo had the idea of using a pendulum to regulate the motion of a time-keeping device, which led to the design of the grandfather clock.

The natural rhythm of the seasons was the important measure of time in an agricultural economy, and the perception of time among the general public was sensed by the position of the sun during the day and length of candles at night. Building small, accurate, and reliable clocks posed a number of technical challenges. The machine tools of the Industrial Revolution had their origins in the equipment developed in the 18th century to make clocks and scientific instruments. In order to develop Great Britain’s trade economy and national security, the government offered a reward equivalent to $200 million today’s economy to the maker of a clock accurate to within ten seconds a day. Captain Cook pioneered the application of such chronometers, enabling him to determine longitude more accurately and create precise charts and maps. During the Industrial Revolution changes in agriculture, manufacturing, and transportation depended in part on scheduling. Workers had to be woken up by alarm clocks in order to arrive on time for their shifts, and to synchronize their activity throughout the day with others in order to maximize the production of goods and services. The efficiency of increasing complexity depended on tighter synchronization.

The market for timepieces grew, and cheap pocket watches became the status symbol for better-paid workers. Mass production of more affordable personal timepieces with interchangeable parts began in the Massachusetts in 1854 at the Waltham Watch Company. In the 20th century clocks without moving parts measured time by the quantum vibrations of atoms in quartz crystals. Scientists now measure time down to the billionth of a second.

Chapter 3: Waiting

Whether waiting is a waste of time or not depends on your point of view and expectations.

1: Waiting Can Be a Waste of Time

If we agree that time is valuable, and look at it as something divisible in chunks, then waiting for some block can be viewed as wasteful, since we could be doing something else during that unit of time instead of just waiting.

The verb waiting means to “remain inactive in a one place in a state of expectation”. Most waiting is unproductive. Security guards provide a useful service and are necessary in today’s complex society. However, seen from another point of view the work that is done is a drain on the economy, since guards are paid basically to wait, watch, and keep certain things from happening.

Whether waiting is a waste of time depends on your point of view and expectations.

2: Why People Don’t Like to Wait

If we agree that time is valuable, and look at it as something divisible in chunks, then waiting for a block of it is wasteful, since we could be doing something else during that time instead of just waiting.

The verb waiting means to “remain inactive in a one place in a state of expectation”. Most waiting is unproductive. Security guards provide a useful service and are necessary in today’s complex society. However, seen from another point of view the work that is done is a drain on the economy, since guards are paid basically to wait, watch, and keep certain things from happening.

There are a number of reasons why people don’t like to wait. The position of waiting for a person or thing can make you feel powerless, and the postponement of gratification for what you want may be unpleasant. If you’re running on a schedule with deadlines feel you may feel you could be doing something else more valuable and/or enjoyable with your time. Some people are offended, feeling that they are as important as those they are waiting for, that they are being treated disrespectfully and having their status lowered. Another of the causes of unhappiness brought on by waiting is one’s lack of control. Many studies have shown a relationship between a sense of control and life satisfaction. It is not so much how much leisure time you have that determines how happy you are, but rather how much control you feel you have over what you do. Regardless of what you decide to do while waiting, the mere fact that you got to decide brings back some feeling of control over the situation.

We expect appointments at the doctor’s office to run on schedule, and get frustrated when they don’t. The third noble truth of Buddhism is that we our suffering can be ended by abandoning unreasonable expectations of how we think things ought to be. Sure, some doctors probably are arrogant, and some may show up late to work. However, understanding the appointment system from the other side of the window may help you be a more patient patient. Our failure sometimes to show up on time or at all, combined with the high price of education, malpractice insurance, and employee salaries leads to doctors needing to overlap and overbook clients in order to maintain a constant stream of income. Appointments should only be looked upon as approximate estimates of when you may be seen. Go on time with something to do, and don’t expect to be admitted at a particular time. A first-come first-served system might be more efficient. Taking a number, and then watching for it to come up on a display would free you from having to worry about losing your place in line, while giving you an idea of how many people are ahead of you in line. Having no idea of how long you have to wait can make it worse.

The next sections of the book contain suggestions on how to learn to relax and be patient and to find things that you enjoy or need to do, thereby reducing the frustration that often arises while waiting.

 

3: Waiting Can Be Good For You

Perhaps the best approach to developing a winning approach to waiting is to start out by mastering waiting. Get control over yourself. Self-control is like a muscle that has to be exercised to remain strong, and waiting gives you an excellent opportunity to practice it. The Chinese/Japanese symbol for “patience” is a combination of two characters—a blade and a heart—representing a combination of patience, tolerance, restraint, and control. It is not always easy to stay above anger, irritation, and resentment. In Japanese combining the character for “patience” with “person” is how you write “ninja”. A ninja is then literally a “patient person”.

One of the best fortune cookie messages I ever saw was taped on a friend’s computer monitor: “She who masters patience, masters all.” Don’t want to be a master of everything? Well, feel free to ignore this, it’s just a fortune cookie message after all. However, people have been saying that “patience is a virtue” since the 14th century, so there may be something to it. Most people who advance in business or stay in relationships have developed patience. It gives you the stamina to meet challenges, achieve career success, and to accommodate the desires and idiosyncrasies of those close to you.

Come to grips with your need for instant gratification. If you need quick rewards in order to act you may not get some of the best things in life, since they often require sustained work over time. You will find that with patience you may eventually get what you want, or find something even better than you weren’t expecting.

The Bible’s Psalm 46:10 starts out with “Be still and know that I am God.” The word “still” comes from the Hebrew word meaning “let go” or “release”. Surrender to how things are. Accept the things that you are powerless to change, such as some of the situations in which you find yourself waiting. No matter how bad it gets, you can console yourself with the reminder that “This too will pass.” Remember what matters: that you are a human being. Be kind, forgiving, and grateful for being alive.

Pay attention and enjoy the moment, whatever it is, as much of the time as possible. Ram Dass coined the phrase “Be here now.” It’s simple enough to remember, and can be used to gently bring your wandering thoughts back to the present. Over time this practice can help you develop concentration, a skill that can be used to direct your thinking in whatever direction you would like. If you are alert you will discover many interesting surprises that might otherwise slip by unnoticed. Be alert. We need more lerts!

There are many mental techniques that you can develop while sitting quietly. For example, practice ignoring distractions. Make a mental tunnel between yourself and what you are concentrating on. If someone enters the room, coughs, or talks to their companion, see if you can maintain your thoughts on what you have been thinking while just letting them be there. You know you’re making real progress when you can ignore someone talking on their cell phone.

Waiting is nature’s way of reminding you to slow down. There’s a reason for everything, so relax and look for clues. What’s the rush? Enjoy the scene and scenery. It’s OK to do nothing at least once in a while. Take the opportunity to decompress and clear your mind. This will make you more effective later.

4: How to Enjoy Waiting

The rate at which time passes is subjective, and is different for each person and situation. Time slows down when you’re anxiously waiting. Remember how long it took for that special someone to arrive, compared to how quickly the time passed once you were together? You have influence over how fast time passes, and can regulating the throttle with the choice and variety of where you put your attention. One of the most satisfying ways to use your time is in activities that put you into a “flow state”, otherwise known by less scientific descriptions as “being in the zone” or “in the groove”.

According to Mihály Csíkszentmihályi, who proposed the concept and has conducted a series of experiments to determine its conditions, you can enter the flow state when you are engaged in self-controlled, goal-related, meaningful action. What brings it on varies for different people depending on their skills and interests. It could happen while knitting, designing a playground, writing a computer program, or performing standup comedy, but there seem to be a set of common components:

Clear goals providing direction and structure.

An opportunity to concentrate, focusing on a limited field of attention.

Immediate feedback as to how well you are doing in order to adjust your performance.

A balance between your ability level and the challenge provided by the activity. You need to feel confident in your abilities, challenged, but not bored.

A sense of personal control over the situation.

 

Signs that you have entered the flow state:

A loss of self-consciousness.

Your focus narrows down to the activity itself.

A lack of awareness of bodily needs such as hunger or fatigue.

Distorted sense of time. Subjective time slows down. You may be surprised afterwards by how far the clock has moved forward when you come out of it.

 

While flow experience may be very productive and intrinsically rewarding, it should perhaps be reserved for longer periods of time since it may take more time to get into, and is something you are less likely going to want to be called out of.

 

Chapter 4: Approaches

Let’s develop some principles and plans that can later be applied to a variety of situations.

1: Two Basic Choices

Do you feel like exerting yourself or just relaxing?

I’m not sure this is going to catch on like Shakespeare’s “To be, or not to be?”, but I propose that the basic decision you face when deciding how to use your time while waiting is “To do, or not to do? That is the question.”

Don’t spend a lot of time agonizing over this choice. There is no right or wrong answer. With practice and increasing self-awareness you should get to the point of being able to decide in a few seconds.

2: Do Something

If you decided to do something, quickly size up the situation and pick something good to do from your available options. This may already be second nature to you, or can become so with practice. In the next chapter we’ll talk about the effect of situations on your choices. Below are some questions you can ask yourself to decide what it is you are going to do, regardless of where you are.

 

Am I going to be interrupted, or do I know more or less how long the wait is going to last?

You have more options if you are in a situation where you know how long the wait is going to last, because in that case you can be wrapping things up about the time the wait ends. If you don’t know how long you’re going to wait, consider the effect of the interruption that is going to come sooner or later.

 

What can I do that I wouldn’t mind being interrupted while doing?

What can I do that I won’t waste time later having to find my place  in order to get back to the point where I left off when tI was interrupted?

If you’re in some place that you don’t know how long the wait will last it’s better to choose things that are easy to stop, so you don’t waste a lot of time later getting back to where you left off. I was in the Motor Vehicles Department one day and took out a stack of papers, which gradually spread out into a few piles. When they called my number I put the stack back together, and went to the window where they had called me. It hadn’t taken more than a minute or so, but by the time I got there I had missed my turn and they had called for the next person. I started to get  snippy but realized they were right. When there’s a line you shouldn’t hold up the people behind you. Saving your time shouldn’t cause someone else to waster theirs.

3: Don’t Do Anything

Chapter 3 started with the suggestion to master doing nothing before moving on to thinking of things to make waiting more productive. Why are you in such a hurry? STOP. Disconnect your devices and unwind. Relax, enjoy the company and scenery. Take it s-l-o-w. Clear your mind, decompress, recharge. Let go of thoughts of worries, work, and family. Contact your original you, your essence deep underneath the layers that have piled up over the years as your personality, experience, relationships, and responsibilities were piled up in layers. Gently remind yourself to let go again when thoughts return.

Doing nothing is always a fallback when you’re not in the mood to do anything else. Your brain continues to process information when you are resting, helping you to better remember what you have recently learned. Doing nothing can provide a welcome break from your routine.

4: Add Some Variety to Your Routine

Try using waiting time as a chance to add variety to your routine, to give your brain circuits or muscles a rest. If you spend you day mostly using your body, do something mental. If you use your mind more than your body, try developing your strength, coordination, or agility. (My lawyer just popped her head in to say “We are not responsible for any consequences of implementing the ideas contained in this book which is intended for entertainment purposes. Consult your doctor or life coach before starting a new fitness or exercise plan or lifestyle change.”). If you always use waiting time to check messages and make calls then do something else. When in doubt, get up and move, have a healthy snack, or get some rest.

Having a variety of projects in different stages keeps things fresh. Over the course of a single week a researcher could be mulling over ideas that might later turn into something useful, be in the middle of research for a current project, be sending the last one out for review, and be reworking some old data in a new way. Someone interested in crafts could be reading books and talking with friends about possible new crafts to learn, practicing calligraphy, and shopping for a frame for a completed painting. Working on projects that are in different stages relieves boredom.

I categorize my todos by how much time they will take to do and where I could do them—whether I am at home in private with all my stuff, or in the public eye with whatever I am able to carry with me. Combinations of times, places, and companions make up the situations that will be discussed in the Chapter 5.

5: Old Standbyes

As I said in the Introduction, a lot of this is common sense, and you probably already have your own repertoire of what you do while waiting. However, considering these old and new standbys may increase your awareness and help you use time more productively and enjoyably. Whatever your experience, try expanding your repertoire. Make notes of things you already do, and ideas for other things you might like to try.

Organize. Make and review lists. Plan the rest of the day, get ready for tomorrow. What is the most important thing that needs to be done? What are three things that you need to do that would make you feel like you have accomplished something? A “thing” should be something that you can do in an hour or less. They can be things you have to do, like appointments or meetings. Get the big one out of the way or the one you’re resisting. When you pack a box it’s better to start with the larger items, around which the smaller pieces can fit. If you begin with the little things you have to do you may not have enough time later to do the more important, larger pieces. Organizing helps you stay on course, and you end up saving time later on as a result.

Read. Books, magazines. There may be some material on tables at the doctor’s office that you don’t own yourself, and while you may get some juicy items, they may be months out of date. Meanwhile you’re picking up the germs left from the other patients sicker than you. Chances are something that you bring yourself will be more interesting and cleaner.

Learn something. Your brain is an organ that grows by interacting with the world. Invest in your continuing education for success in life and update your skills to benefit your career. Learning about new things enriches your life, and makes it easier to find common ground with other people. Learn something new, and right away you’ll have new antennae extensions that will begin receiving new information. You’ll start noticing conversations and connections that would have otherwise slipped by unnoticed. Curious there might be more waiting out there for you? They say the more foreign languages you learn, the more worlds you live in. How many lives do you want to have? You don’t need to become fluent, just learn the 200 most important words to express the basics.

Exercise your mind. Use it or lose it. Even in old age the brain can grow new neurons. Mental stimulation improves its function, and like physical exercise it helps protect against cognitive decline. Crossword and sudoku puzzles can provide a workout. Recalling enjoyable memories is a win-win—giving your memory a workout while creating a pleasant sensation. Memorize a poem—it’s a mental challenge, and makes you richer. Afterwards it will be something that you can use for a memory exercise, and it once reviewed and logged into in your long term memory it can never be lost or stolen. Learn sign language. The combination of a new grammar, facial expressions, and hand gestures activates a new combination of brain areas.

Exercise your body. Stretch, do isometrics. My physical therapist said to give yourself a couple of weeks on one level before increasing 20%. It took a long time to get out of shape so don’t be in a hurry to try to get fit. This is a good use of your time that might otherwise be wasted.

Things to do with (e)paper. Exercise your communication skills or creativity. Write a letter, note, or postcard. Draw a picture, write a poem, or compose a song. Beethoven sometimes carried his notebooks with him so that he could compose if an idea came to mind or he was waiting.

Enjoy / get inspired. Listen to music. Music is played at us everywhere we go these days, but we usually don’t take the time to pay close attention to it. Develop an appreciation of classical music—it stands up better to repeated listening. Try something from another culture or time period. Look at a photo album, read poetry, stories. Get the good stuff.

Talk with other people. Be friendly to those around you who are also waiting, while practicing paying attention. Be ready for non-verbal cues that they want to be left alone. Be respectful of other peoples’ time and space—they may be in the midst of enjoying using their waiting time to do something by themselves.

Daydream. Scientists have begun to view daydreaming as such a fundamental feature of the human mind as to consider it the “default” mode of thought. Many believe that the new associations and connections that a more relaxed style of thinking fosters are crucial to the creative process. Free your mind from your surroundings and imagine things that don’t actually exist yet. The distinct pattern of brain areas that are activated while daydreaming is most engaged when performing a task that requires little attention, like doodling or staring into space. Maintain just enough awareness to notice when your daydream has touched on a useful idea.

Tune in/out. Pray. Meditate. Focus on what you’re thinking and feeling. Become aware of your breathing. Try something that reinforces your humanity, like developing compassion and self-awareness.

6: New Standbyes

(Re)focus on short and long term goals. What is that you want get done in the next days, week, month, years? Try writing a mission statement—what’s important to you? What are your core values, beliefs, and priorities? Keep it simple and limit it to a few sentences. Develop a plan for achieving your goals. Make a commitment to stick to it.

Figure stuff out. Sometimes you get stuck at a roadblock. Think up a few ways you can try to get around a problem. Be careful not to get stuck in an unproductive stewing session. Try a thought experiment, following the implications of a statement beginning with a phrase such as “What would happen if…?” Evidently this is how Einstein came up with the theory of Relativity, thinking about what it would be like to ride on a beam of light, which led to a reformulating of modern physics. Arthur Fry was mulling over how to make bookmarks that would stick in a book when he came up with the idea for Post-It notes, which became one of the most successful office products.

Increase your options. Instead of weighing the pros and cons of a single course of action, think of as many options as you can.

Make a gift or favor list. What would you like to do with your family or companions that you have been putting off? What would they like for their next birthday or holiday? How could you surprise them this week? Try going beyond just pleasing them, or even delighting. What would blow them away, something they would always remember?

Play. Find something that is completely unproductive. If it’s with kids find a way to gently return to your routine when the time comes so that you don’t leave them in the lurch. Teach your dog a new trick. Teach yourself a new trick.

Take some time off. Take off an afternoon, morning, or day a week. Find a quiet private space in order to maximize the benefit—going out in public probably won’t be as relaxing. Plan ahead. You may need to schedule this. Tell everyone that you’re going to be “busy” and unavailable.

Mental rehearsing. The most efficient way to learn may be to alternate  physical practice with thinking through an activity. Use short blocks of time to prepare for challenging tasks, interviews, competitions, sales calls, presentations, managing, parenting, etc. Perform steps such as the following when you’re in a situation where you won’t be interrupted:

Close your eyes and relax. Breathe deeply, exhale slowly.

Imagine stress leaving your body sequentially from the soles of your feet to your scalp.

Visualize the challenge. Tell yourself confidently that you have the ability to do it.

Imagine what you will be seeing before, during, and after the task.

Mentally rehearse successfully performing the task. Visualize the result. Repeat the sequence six times.

Praise yourself.

Rub your face and hands, open your eyes.

 

7: Planning and Preparation

There are two main types of planning that need to be done in advance in order to get consistent high returns from your spare moments:

(1) Long Term planning. Determine what your goals are in life. What do you want to accomplish? What would you do if you had time that would make your life better? What part of this could be done in small chunks of time?

(2) Short term planning. How can you clear out small jobs that need to get done in order to clear out time later to use more enjoyably? What habits can you create so that you won’t expend unnecessary mental energy? Develop a repertoire of things you can do matched to the length of time and locations you find yourself in.

Stretch. Learn a set of stretches, yoga postures, or exercises that you can do in different situations based on the amount of time it takes to do them, time of day, place, amount of privacy, dress, etc. Print them out for a reference until you have memorized the routine.

Prepare a survival kit. Prepare a waiting survival kit in a backpack or other carrying bag for you pack—starting with such popular items as paper, stationary, postcards, writing implements, something to study, a magazine, or maybe a book of poetry and 20 sign or foreign language flash cards. Load up a portable listening device with favorite music. Planning a survival kit is kind of like getting a suitcase ready for a journey. Start with what you’d like to take, and then jettison the least productive stuff. Leave it close to the door so you can grad it on the way out. If you have young kids add puzzle and coloring books, crayons, paper, magazines, things you don’t mind losing, a deck of cards, note cards cut from card stock, stickers, and a list of games, like “I spy…”, 20 questions, Spot the {color} car, “Don’t step on the cracks”, and “If you could go anywhere where would you choose?” etc.

A stitch in time saves nine. Sometimes a few seconds of preparation makes the difference in rescuing an hour later. The little bit of time it takes to prepare to use waiting time in an enjoyable and productive way can make a difference later on.

The next section explores planning your routine in order to avoid waiting in the first place.

8: Avoid Waiting

I’ve been told that one of the best martial arts skills is developing one’s speed to run away. It’s even better to avoid the fight if you can in the first place. So far our Win at Waiting has dealt with finding ways to use the time that would otherwise be wasted in productive and enjoyable ways. However, the best defense is often a strong offense. Work on achieving and maintaining clarity about avoiding situations where you will have to wait or otherwise waste time. You have to be quick, sometimes it happens in a matter of seconds, you make a decision and it puts you on the slow road. You probably already do this, and may be more alert having thought about using waiting times to better advantage, but here are a couple of tips:

Plan your outings when there is less traffic. Experiment with different times of the day/days of the week. Shop at 7:00 pm or at times most people are watching TV, like during the Superbowl. Avoid going out at lunch time and rush hour.

Group your errands so that you make the trip in and out of your neighborhood less often. Plan your route to avoid doubling back and organize your shopping list by sections of the store. Being organized will reduce the frequency of forgetting something. Having to make a special trip for just one item is annoying, especially when the last place that is open is far away.

Move somewhere where you can walk or bike to work or shopping. Do your shopping with a friend you’d like to spend more time with.

Make appointments and flight reservations early in the day. There is a better chance that the schedule won’t get backed up by delays.

9: Advanced Techniques: How to Save Time Using Public Transportation

Public transportation in most cities in the United States is an embarrassment compared with many other countries. Our construction of spread-out suburbs has created an infrastructure that wastes time and energy. One proof of thorough mastery and super-efficient application of the strategies presented in this book will be your ability to ride public transportation and actually save time. It is possible. Here are some inspiring anecdotes:

Duke Ellington wrote a lot of music on the road, even on napkins in restaurants.

Erroll Garner didn’t read music, so when he came up with “Misty” on an airplane he had to keep humming it to himself until he was able to get to a piano and get the tune transcribed.

J.K. Rowling came up with the idea for Harry Potter riding on a train.

In addition to writing nights and weekends, Charles Ives composed while commuting to his insurance job.

Peter Brett wrote his first novel on his mobile phone riding the New York subway.

Chapter 5: Situations

Your time will be used most effectively when you choose to do something that best matches the situation.

A: Circumstances

For the purposes of this discussion let’s define “circumstance” as the  conditions that influence an activity. We’ll start with simple circumstances dictated by people, places, and amount of time. Afterwards we’ll combine circumstances to form more complex situations.

People. What are some things you can do, depending on the people you are with?

Make a list of things that can be done alone, for example sit ups, knee bends, isometrics, studying vocabulary flash cards, mental rehearsing, planning, reviewing, and organizing. You might want to mark each item with one of two symbols or color code to put them into two sub-lists, one for those things you can do when you have privacy, and the other that can be done  in public.

Make another list of things that can be done with other people,  like reminisce, plan, brainstorm, quiz each other, discover something new, recite memorized poetry, dance, massage shoulders, try to make each other laugh, see who can hold their breath longest, stare into each others’ eyes, come up with something to do during commercials, or take a walk. Take advantage of the power of two or more minds focused on a single task. You’ll have enough chances to do the solo activities when you’re alone, so avoid things like texting, making phone calls, etc.

 

Places. What are some things you can do, depending on the place where you are? Your choices will be affected by how much privacy you have or need, and where you are. Some of the items on your list are best done when others can’t see and/or hear you, some can be done anywhere.

Make lists of things you can do while waiting in different places, such as at work, in school, on a plane, in a store, or at a friend’s.

 

Amount of time. What are some things you can do, depending on the amount of time you are expecting to wait, and whether you can predict how long that will be or not? What things are best done when you know how long the wait is going to be, and which can be interrupted at any time for those situations when you don’t know?

What can you do in less than a minute, or for 5, 10, 20, or more minutes? Below are a few suggestions. Make your own list and increase your options.

.5 minutes: stretch hands, arms, shoulders, legs, eyes, blink repeatedly to lubricate eyes, look into distance to let eyes change focal length, breathe deeply, exhale fully.

1 minute: walk around, use your muscles.

5 minutes: do a puzzle, pray, visualize, plan a birthday or start thinking about an anniversary.

10 minutes: reconnect with goals, write a letter, wash some clothes, write a limerick.

30 minutes: meditate, walk the dog, write a poem or haiku, do yoga or core exercise.

60 minutes: work on goals, mission statement, work in garden.

Try to come up with as many ideas as you can so that you’ll have more to work with when considering the situations discussed in the next section.

 

2: Situations

Your time will be used most effectively when you choose to do (or not do) something that best matches the situation, a particular combination of the three conditions discussed in the last section of people, place, and amount of time.

Here are some situations you may be familiar with:

Waiting for someone to get ready to go out. People: your significant other, members of your family, or friends. Place: Home. Time: approximately 5-30 minutes. Negatives: The frustration in this situation is heightened because you don’t know how long the wait is going to last, and because you are dressed up and may be concerned about being late. Positives: You’re at home, you have all your stuff, have your privacy, and probably have plenty of things to pick from. Do something that won’t mess your clothes and that you can drop at a moment’s notice, like doing some light cleaning near the door, organizing shopping lists, planning the next meal, or learning to play a musical instrument.

Waiting for an appointment. People: strangers. Place: doctor’s office. Time: approximately 10-40 minutes. Negatives: Potentially a long wait of unknown length, anticipation of unpleasant procedures, surrounded by sick people. Positives: You knew this one was coming and could have prepared for a long wait and cleared out your schedule, so you’re not in a hurry. No traffic, fairly comfortable chairs. Prepare to get lots of work done, or let your mind go. Try making up stories about other patients such as: “what is the most amazing fact about them that you would never guess from their demeanor?”, “what would they tell you if you got to know them?”, “what are they hiding?”, or “where would they like to go on vacation?” Warnings: Be discreet in taking stock of them and don’t stare. Talking with them about the long wait will interfere with your fantasy.

Waiting for a plane. People: strangers. Place: in airport, behind security screening. Time: 30 minutes to 8 hours or more. Negatives. You’ve gone through security and it’s hard to leave the gate area. Limited and expensive options for food and shopping. Long wait could turn into overnight stay, complicating work and family commitments. Positives: you’re cut off from most other responsibilities. Sooner or later connects to subsequent flight of known duration. A shared pain is easier to bear, commiserating with other passengers may help.  Walk, stretch, eat, use the facilities. Save sitting for the flight.

Waiting in line. People: strangers or friends/family. Place: grocery store, bank, post office, etc. Time: 2 - 10 minutes. Negatives: You worry that you may have picked the slowest line. Positives: You know where you are in line and have a rough idea how long the wait is going to take, unless things go wrong and the person in front of you has some issue. Talk with your companions, if you have any. If you’re alone, try standing on one foot and then the other for about 15 seconds at a time. Quickly size up what’s in other peoples’ carts and imagine the dinner party they are planning. See how many headlines you can memorize from the gossip magazines in the rack. Think of something nice you can do for someone. Count your blessings.

Waiting at a stoplight. People: alone or with passenger(s). Place: your car. Time: 1-3 minutes. Negatives: waste of fuel. Positives: you’re in your own climate-controlled space. No one talks to you. This is the only time while driving that you can really let your mind wander, or fiddle with things in your car. Breathe, relax, stretch, including your eyes by looking past the light into the distance.

On hold on the telephone. People: alone. Place: home or office. Time: 1-3 minutes or more. Negatives: Don’t know how long it will last, repetitive music and annoying menu navigation and encouragements from answering system. Positives: Can be doing anything you like because other person can’t see you. Get a speaker phone or earpiece so that you can be doing other things more comfortably while on hold. Amuse yourself by imitating the tone of the recorded voice. Mumble in order to confound the voice recognition system and be connected to a representative more promptly. Exercise, stretch, eat, drink water.

Errands with the kids. People: dependents. Place: around town. Time: approximately .75 - 2 hours. Negatives: mood gradually deteriorates as blood sugar goes down and fatigue increases. Attention demanded by children reduces driver’s ability to concentrate on driving. Positives: car provides storage for variety of diversions, children are strapped in by seat belts. Be glad you brought along a travel survival kit, including such things as snacks, water, towels, handheld games, notepad, pencils, small toys, sunglasses, kids music, TV program/movie.

If you haven’t done so already, jot down some ideas of what you could do in public and in private depending on who you are with and how long you expect to be waiting. You can make your own worksheet like the one that follows in the next section or download one from lovelythinking.com.

You may also enjoy the quotes at the end of Chapter 6 from a variety of authors selected for your enjoyment from the last 2500 years.

I hope after reading this book and doing some brainstorming that you will have more options for to do while waiting, and that as a result you’ll be able to use that time more enjoyably and productively. I hope that the time you save can be used to enjoy life and the time you have with those you are with along the way. Time is precious, so use it wisely!

3: Worksheet

 

Private
	

Public
	

 

 
	

 
	

:30

 
	

 
	

1:00

 
	

 
	

5:00

 
	

 
	

10:00

 
	

 
	

20:00

 
	

 
	

30:00

 
	

 
	

60:00

 

 

4: Answers

 

Private
	

Public
	

 

Jumping jacks, stretch your face.
	

Breathe deeply through nose, exhale fully through mouth, repeat 3X.
	

:30

Run in place. Knee bends.
	

Review flash cards. Say “hello” to someone.
	

1:00

Practice ukelele.
	

Plan for the rest of the day and tomorrow, Think of something nice to do for someone you care about.
	

5:00

Do some chore, clean or organize something.
	

Review personal goals. Work on patience. Write a postcard.
	

10:00

Meditate.
	

Write a letter. Memorize a poem. Call your mom.
	

20:00

Take a nap.Give your dog a bath.
	

Write a love letter.
	

30:00

Prepare for a romantic evening. Have a workout. Bake a pie. Tackle a home improvement project. Give yourself a pedicure. Take a bubble bath.
	

Write your autobiography.
	

60:00

 

 

 

Chapter 6: For Further Study

Studying time management can itself be a good use of time. Here are a few titles to help put things in perspective.

1: Bibliography

Covey, Stephen. The Seven Habits of Highly Effective People. New York: Simon + Schuster, 1989. Helps set priorities based on values and roles.

Csíkszentmihályi, Mihály. Flow: The Psychology of Optimal Experience. New York: Harper and Row, 1990. Creative activity is a satisfying use of time.

Hawking, Steven. A Brief History of Time. London: Bantam Press, 1998. How did the universe begin, and does time always flow forward?.

Isaacson, Walter. Einstein: His Life and Universe. New York: Simon + Schuster, 2007. The story of a great thinker and his discoveries about the atom, universe, and time.

Lewinson, Mark. The Complete Beatles Chronicles. New York: Harmony Books, 1992. The lads from Liverpool got a lot done in just a few years.

Pausch, Randy and Jeffrey Zaslow. The Last Lecture. New York: Hyperion, 2008. Lessons learned from a terminal cancer patient. We’re all terminal cases, but most of us aren’t as positive or aware.

Rath, Tom. Eat Move Sleep: How Small Choices Lead to Big Changes. Missionday, 2013. Lots of practical information presented in manageable bites.

Weisman, Alan. The World Without Us. New York: Thomas Dunne Books, 2007. What would happen if humans disappeared?

2: Join the Community

Watch for updates and additional material online at lovelythinking.com, where you can join in the conversation and share your suggestions for what to do while waiting.

3: Quotes

No one can dip his feet in the same river twice. – Heraclitus, 475 BC

Time is the most valuable thing a man can spend. – Theophrasmus, 287 BC

The whole life of a man is but a point of time; let us enjoy it. – Plutarch, 122 BC

Waiting is not mere empty hoping. It has the inner certainty of reaching the goal. - I Ching, 50 BC

All past time is lost time; the very day we are now spending is shared between ourselves and death. – Seneca, 85

Who forces time is pushed back by time; who yields to time finds time on his side. - The Talmud, 200

What then is time? If no one asks me, I know what it is. If I wish to explain it to him who asks, I do not know. - Saint Augustine, 410

All my possessions for a moment of time.  -Elizabeth I, 1603

Tomorrow, and tomorrow, and tomorrow, Creeps in this petty pace from day to day. - William Shakespeare, 1616 As if you could kill time without injuring eternity. - Henry David Thoreau, 1862

Time is what we want most, but... what we use worst. - William Penn, 1718

I recommend you to take care of the minutes, for the hours will take care of themselves. - Lord Chesterfield, 1773

Take time for all things: great haste makes great waste. - Benjamin Franklin, 1790

Lost time is never found again. - Benjamin Franklin, 1705

Dost thou love life? Then do not squander time, for that is the stuff life is made of. - Benjamin Franklin, 1705

Time is money. - Benjamin Franklin, 1705

Never leave that till tomorrow which you can do today. To me every hour of the light and dark is a miracle, every cubic inch of space is a miracle. - Benjamin Franklin, 1705

Leisure is the time for doing something useful. This leisure the diligent person will obtain the lazy one never. - Benjamin Franklin, 1705

Employ thy time well, if thou meanest to gain leisure. - Benjamin Franklin, 1705

Determine never to be idle. No person will have occasion to complain of the want of time who never loses any. It is wonderful how much may be done if we are always doing. - Thomas Jefferson, 1826

Much may be done in those little shreds and patches of time which every day produces, and which most men throw away. - Charles Caleb Colton, 1832

One always has time enough, if one will apply it well. - Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, 1832

As if you could kill time without injuring eternity. - Henry David Thoreau, 1862

Time is but the stream I go a-fishing in. - Henry David Thoreau, 1862

Time is a great teacher, but unfortunately it kills all its pupils. - Louis Hector Berlioz, 1869

You will never find time for anything. If you want time you must make it. - Charles Buxton, 1871

Guard well your spare moments. They are like uncut diamonds. Discard them and their value will never be known. Improve them and they will become the brightest gems in a useful life. - Ralph Waldo Emerson, 1882

How much of human life is lost in waiting. - Ralph Waldo Emerson, 1882

A man who dares to waste one hour of time has not discovered the value of life. - Charles Darwin, 1882

We should not say that one man&apos;s hour is worth another man&apos;s hour, but rather that one man during an hour is worth just as much as another man during an hour. Time is everything, man is nothing: he is at the most time&apos;s carcass. - Karl Marx, 1883

Men talk of killing time, while time quietly kills them.  - Dion Boucicault, 1890

The two most powerful warriors are patience and time. Leo Tolstoy, 1910

Day, n.  A period of twenty-four hours, mostly misspent. - Ambrose Bierce, 1914

What we love to do we find time to do. - John L. Spalding, 1916

Time is what keeps everything from happening at once. - Ray Cummings, 1922

There is time for everything. - Thomas Edison, 1931

There&apos;s time enough, but none to spare. - Charles W. Chestnut, 1932

Half our life is spent trying to find something to do with the time we have rushed through life trying to save. - Will Rogers, 1935

I have noticed that the people who are late are often so much jollier than the people who have to wait for them. - E.V. Lucas, 1938

Time spent with cats is never wasted. - Sigmund Freud, 1939

It has been my observation that most people get ahead during the time that others waste. - Henry Ford, 1947

The only reason for time is so that everything doesn’t happen at once. - Albert Einstein, 1955

Time and space are modes by which we think and not conditions in which we exist. - Albert Einstein, 1955

When forced to summarize the gerneal theory of relativity in one sentence: Time and space and gravitation have no separate existence from matter.” – Albert Einstein, 1955

Mickey Mouse popped out of my mind onto a drawing pad 20 years ago on a train ride from Manhattan to Hollywood at a time when business fortunes of my brother Roy and myself were at lowest ebb and disaster seemed right around the corner. - Walt Disney, 1966

Time is the fire in which we burn. - Delmore Schwartz 1966

We didn&apos;t lose the game; we just ran out of time. - Vince Lombardi, 1970

There is time for work. And time for love. That leaves no other time! - Coco Chanel, 1971

Time flies like the wind. Fruit flies like bananas. - Groucho Marx, 1977

I find television very educating. Every time somebody turns on the set, I go into the other room and read a book. - Groucho Marx  1997.

Any time you&apos;ve got nothing to do and lots of time to do it come on up. - Mae West, 1980

Better late than early. – Robert Willey, 1990

Every morning you are handed 24 golden hours. They are one of the few things in this world that you get free of charge. If you had all the money in the world, you couldn&apos;t buy an extra hour. What will you do with this priceless treasure? - Anonymous

Time is like a snowflake—it melts away while we try to decide what to do with it. - Anonymous

 

About the Author

Robert Willey began a series of art/life performances in 1991 called “Peace Pieces”, which included a year of avoiding negative words (saying as much as possible in the positive form—what you want rather than what you don’t want), a CD of the same name, and a plan for a book about what to do while waiting.

Willey presently directs the Music Media Production and Industry program at Ball State University. Visit lovelythinking.com for conversation and updates for this book, and robertwilley.com to find out about his new age jazz bossa nova folk electronic instrumental experimental music.

Acknowledgements

Thanks to Maria Oneide Willey for her good sense, insight, and perspective. Conversations with her led to making this approach more balanced. She suggested emphasizing quality of time rather than efficiency, and to use this approach to finish one’s work out in the world, in order to be freer and more present afterwards.

The hour glass graphic on the cover was designed by Biju Subhash.
        " />
    
</ScrollView>